A Guide to the Social Science Research Council records, Economics Initiative, Record Group 3, Series 1 FA1196 FA1196
Rockefeller Archive Center
Social Science Research Council records, Economics Initiative, Record Group 3, Series 1
1983-1994
Rockefeller Archive Center
Social Science Research Council
FA1196
4.46 Cubic Feet 10 letter-size document boxes, 1 legal-size document box, and 1 half-letter document box
Arrangement
The Social Science Research Council archives are arranged into three record groups distinguished by the date of their donation to the Archive Center. Accession 1 (Record Group 1) consists of the documents received by the Archive Center in 1990; Accession 2 (Record Group 2) was transferred to the Archive Center in 1994; Record Group 3 was transferred to the Archive Center in 2017-2018.
Within series the records are primarily arranged in original order.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Social Science Research Council records were donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center in 1990 and record transfers continue periodically. The records in this series were received in 2017-2018.
Biographical / Historical
The Social Science Research Council (SSRC) is a private, not-for-profit organization established in 1923 to advance research in the social sciences. The SSRC came into being through the initiatives of Wesley C. Mitchell and Charles E. Merriam, members of the American Political Science Association. Representatives of the American Economic Association, the American Sociological Society, the American Statistical Association, the American Historical Association and the American Psychological Association assisted Merriam and his associates in forming the SSRC. They invited the participation of other national associations in anthropology, history, and psychology, many of which designated representatives to the SSRC in the year following its incorporation on December 27, 1924.
To support its work, the SSRC turned not to the U.S. government, whose support seemed more appropriate for the natural sciences, but to private foundations. For the first fifty years, well over three-quarters of the SSRC's funding was provided by the Russell Sage Foundation, the Ford Foundation, the Carnegie Corporation, and two Rockefeller philanthropies, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial and the Rockefeller Foundation. By the 1970s, however, funds for some special projects were obtained from federal agencies.
Scope and Contents
The Economics Initiative series contains correspondence, papers and drafts, reports, periodicals, meeting records, and associated background information.
Other Finding Aids
Other finding aids documenting Social Science Research Council records include:
FA021 Social Science Research Council records, Record Group 1 and Record Group 2 FA1481 Social Science Research Council records, East Asia/Indochina, RG 3, Series 2
- Economics Initiative, 1983-1994; 1
  - SSRC Committee for Research on the Urban Underclass - Why Black Men are Doing Worse in the Labor Market: A Review of Supply Side and Demand-Side Explanations, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Vienna Centre - Strategies for European Cooperation in Social Sciences, Vienna Centre-UNESCO Conference, 1985 November 27-December 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Social Europe, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Facts and Figures (European Cultural Foundation), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - SSRC - Fellowships and Grants for Training and Research to be Offered in 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Polish Perspectives, Quarterly Review, Warsaw, Volume XXIX, 1986 Spring (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sociologia, Volume 1 and 2, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - New Challenges for Europe after 1989 (The Consortium for the Study of European Transition), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - SSRC Annual Report 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Eureka, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Tarki, Budapest, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - European Political Data Newsletter, 1984 March-1988 December (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Centre for European Policy Studies (CEPS) Newletter, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Centre for European Policy Studies (CEPS) Working Documents, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Studia I Materialy - Political and Economic Challenges to Social Policy, Warsaw, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - HungInfo - Hungarian Social Sciences and Humanities - Periodicals, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Journal of European Economic History, Rome, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - The Journal of European Economic History, Rome, 1983-1987 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - The Journal of European Economic History, Rome, 1988-1991 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Journal of International Affairs - Europe: Interdependence and the Marshall Plan Heritage, Vol. 41, No. 2, 1988 Summer (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Eastern European Politics and Societies (EEPS) Journal, University of California Press, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
  - Eastern European Politics and Societies (EEPS) Journal, University of California Press, 1989-1992 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Tarsadalmi Riport 1990 (Tarki), Budapest (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Heft 2-89 - 1999, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - UNDP - Development Co-operation Vietnam Report 1989 and 1990, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - National Academy of Sciences - Committee on National Statistics, Sixty-First Meeting, 1993 May 14 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 2017:018:017 - Reinventing Vietnamese Socialism - Bound Volume (Box 8)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Special format items have been separated from the file and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
  - UNDP - Draft Report of the Cambodia Infrastructure Survey Mission, 1990 April (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Comparative Project on Human Resource Development and Behavior in Latin America and Southeast Asia, 1983 September (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Behrman Project (Bill S.) (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Draft Proposal for a Program on Transitions to Market Economies, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Cambodia - Agenda for Rehabilitation and Reconstruction, The World Bank, East Asia and Pacific Region, Country Department I, 1992 June (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Funding - Economics Initiative (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Funding - Raw Data (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - The Housing Budget in Transition: Comparing Patterns of income and Expenditure in Poland and the U.S., 1993 March (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Dirty Money and Education: Economic-Class Resources and Entrepreneurship in Czechoslovakia, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - The Housing Budget in Transition, 1993 March 19-21 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Project Link, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - MESA Newsletter. Volume 12, No. 4, 1991 November (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Comparative Development of Market Economies - Foundation Correspondence, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Bill Schraadenbach - Foundation Information and Reports, 1990s (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - A Request to the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation for a Grant to Support a Project on Market Emergence and Formation, 1994 October 24 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Committee for Research on Global Environmental Change, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Workshop on Economic Transitions, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Bill Schraadenbach - Foundation Information and Reports, 1991-1994 (Box 12, Folder 4)